Guide to the Office of Human Resources Reference Collection, 1950-[ongoing] UA.01.11.0031
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of Human Resources Reference collection
1950-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.11.0031
2.5 Linear Feet
The Office of Human Resources Reference Collection contains files of memoranda, personnel policy notices, employee handbooks and newsletters, policy manuals, news clippings, literature on training opportunities, and other materials concerning the personnel management functions of the University. Materials date from the early 1950s through the 1990s. Major subjects include benefits, wages and salaries, upward mobility programs and training, services for employees, employee awards and appreciation events, and personnel policies and work rules. This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
2,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Office of Human Resources Reference Collection was compiled by University Archives staff from a variety of sources for reference and research.
Historical Note
Chronology List
1948/1949 The position of Personnel Director first appeared in the University Bulletin. The appointee, Walter G. Cooper, reported to the Business Manager and Comptroller. The Personnel Department was given authority over all "employees of the University who are not directly connected in a professional capacity with its social or academic activities."
1969/1970 The Personnel Department had the following structure: Director, Wage and Salary, Personnel Records, Employment Office, Medical Center Personnel, Training and Development, Cost Reduction
1980-1982 The Human Resources division was created and structured as follows: Director (an Assistant Vice President), Benefits and Records, Employee Relations, Employee Services, Wage and Salary, Human Resources Development, Employment Office, Labor Relations
1997 Administration, Benefits Administration, Temporary Services, Employee Occupational Health Services, Learning/Training and Organizational Development, Rewards and Recognition [formerly Wage and Salary], Recruitment.
2000 The Human Resources division became headed by a Vice President
Collection Overview
The Office of Human Resources Reference Collection contains files of memoranda, personnel policy notices, employee handbooks and newsletters; policy manuals; news clippings, brochures, and other printed materials. The collection is organized in five series: 1) Management 2) Personnel Department 3) Awards 4) Training 5) Benefits
Related Material
Labor Unions Reference Collection, 1965-1982.
University Archives, Duke University.
Office of Human Resources records, 1979-[ongoing].
Duke University Archives, Duke University.
Academic Council Records see Non-Academic Employees Committee
University Archives, Duke University.
Student Organizations Reference Collection, 1913-ongoing. see Student-Employee Relations Coalition
University Archives, Duke University.
College personnel management -- North Carolina -- Durham; Employee fringe benefits -- North Carolina -- Durham; Labor unions -- North Carolina -- Durham; College teachers -- Retirement -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Duke University -- Employees; Duke University -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Duke University -- Quarter Century Club; Duke University. Office of Human Resources; Duke University. University Archives; Duke University -- Personnel management; Duke University. Personnel Department -- History
- Management
  - Administration Memoranda, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Department Supervisors' Manual, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Supervisors' Handbook, 1982/1986 (Box 1)
  - "Guideline" [supervisors' newsletter], 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Area wage survey, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Wage and salary workshop handbook, [1974-1978] (Box 1)
  - Position classification guide, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Position description and classification proposal [1967] (Box 1)
  - A Study of the Duke University Personnel Management System, 1980 [report] (Box 1)
  - Work Culture Task Force, 1998 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Drug-free work environment, 1998 (Box 1)
- Personnel Department
  - Employment office, 1970-1986 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Department Clippings (Box 1)
  - Personnel Department Memoranda, circa 1951-1990 + undated (8f) (Box 1)
  - Personnel notices, circa 1969-1994 (Box 1)
  - Severe weather policy, 1974/1975 (Box 1)
  - Employee Life [newsletter], 1968 (Box 1)
  - Update: Duke Employees News Release circa 1973-1988 (Box 1)
  - Employee handbooks and work rules, 1960-1974 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Personnel Policy Manual, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Personnel Policy Manual, superseded material, 1974-1981 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Duke University Personnel Policy Manual, superseded material, 1981-1996 (2 folder) (Box 2)
  - Duke University Personnel Policy Manual, February, 1985 (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Awards
  - Service awards, 1968- (includes Presidential and Quarter-Century awards) (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Training
  - Employee training, memoranda and schedules, 1967-1986 (Box 2)
  - Training and Organizational Development, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
  - Training and Organizational Development Job Enhancement Program, 1985, 1987 (Box 2)
  - University Center for Management and Professional Development, 1994-1997 (Box 2)
  - Learning and Organizational Development, 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - Paths for Employee Progress, [1971] and Critical needs job training, circa 1990 (Box 2)
- Benefits
  - Benefits, general, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Benefits: faculty and staff, 1957-1965 (Box 2)
  - Day Care Assistance, 1971- (Box 2)
  - Faculty benefits handbooks, 1969, 1973, 1987 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Staff benefits and policy handbooks, 1974, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Staff benefits guides, 1989 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Faculty and staff retirement plan, circa 1950 (Box 2)
  - Retirement planning guide for faculty, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Employees' retirement plan, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Staff Benefits Guide and Packets, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Life insurance, 1962-1974 (Box 2)
  - Disability insurance, 1971-1991 (Box 2)
  - Tuition benefit, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Comparable benefits for same-sex spousal equivalents, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Benefits Fair/Open enrollment, 1999/2000 (Box 2)
  - Employee and family programs, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Child and family programs, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Employee programs, misc. (Box 2)
  - Personal Assistance Service (Box 2)
  - Employee week, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Employee appreciation posters, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Supervisor's Handbook, circa 1982 (Box 2)
  - Live for Life Health Promotion, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Handbooks and literature (duplicates) (Box 2)